<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/DiSA-DHIL/ATN-Schema/refs/heads/main/dist/ATN.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/DiSA-DHIL/ATN-Schema/refs/heads/main/dist/ATN.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="FruBjornsonofMarkerville1">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Fru Bjornson of Markerville</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcriber</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:SL1">Sydney Lines</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:SL1">Sydney Lines</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Digital Scholarship in the Arts</distributor>
                <distributor>Digital Humanities Innovation Lab</distributor>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>
                    <!--Information about the source file. If it's
                  a primary source, use a <bibl> or <msDesc>;
                  if born digital, use <p>Born Digital</p>-->
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <schemaRef url="https://github.com/DiSA-DHIL/ATN-Schema/blob/main/sch/ATN.odd"/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="atn:DocType" target="atn:PrimarySource"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb n="45"/>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Fru Bjornson of Markerville</head>
                <opener>
                    <byline>By <name ref="pers:LGS1">Laura Goodman Salverson</name></byline>
                    <byline>Illustrated by <name ref="pers:RF1">Roy Fisher</name></byline>
                </opener>
                <p><trait type="ethnicity"><label>Ethnicity</label><desc>German</desc></trait>Herr Johann was ever a man with laughter close to his lips and an abundant imagination. Hence, it comes about that his sturdy old house, standing in the midst of thriving grainfields and fertile pastures that roll on jubilantly towards the Great Foot Hills is an eloquent memorial to deeds well done. For the old house hugs a story as most old houses do and, the story is the story of Canada in the making.</p>
                <p>Life and death have hobnobbed beneath its grey gables; success and failure touched cold shoulders there; heartaches and hardships followed in succession, yet hope has never quitted that ancient rooftree.</p>
                <p>Weatherbeaten and scarred, its timbers still sound at the core, the old house broods upon the golden grainfields, the emerald pastures dotted with fancy stock and pedigreed sheep, and the tender little maples copse, sprung from seedlings planted by Herr Johann when he, and his house, was young and the rich fields round them was unbroken virgin prairie.</p>
                <p>Herr Johann is grey now and walks with a slight limp, (even the limp has a story), his years number seventy; yet to hear him laugh or to read his poetry, or to see him dash through the innumerable chores of a big farm is to realize that age is a bogey no longer to be feared.</p>
                <p>Some say there is one prime reason for Herr Johann's sprightliness. His wife, a wee pocket-edition of wmoanhood is a veritable dynamo of activity. Even molasses hurries in her hands! So say the neighbors. Nothing daunts her. Neither Victorian pruderiers, nor flapper cruditites disturb her equilibrium. Of her effects upon the countryside the same cannot be said. Little she is but sometimes terrible in her littleness!</p>
                <p>Little, yes, but very disturbing to medieval consciences! Old and workworn, she till manages her household, makes all her butter and cheese and <q>skyr</q> (the Icelander's equivalent for ice cream) drives and smokes her meat and in her spare time spins the finest of wool and runs a knitting machine for good profit. Then, too, madam turns a sonnet now and again or airs her views on the rural telephone.</p>
                </div>
            <div>
                <head><q>Men Are All Alike</q></head>
                <p>But <trait type="ethnicity"><label>Ethnicity</label><desc>Icelandic</desc></trait>Fru Bjornson is not without pity. When the <q>honorable member</q> for Saskatchewan was billeted at her house––just before the big national celebration it was, and the great man booked to address his compatriots––she came valiantly to his rescue. Over the breakfast table gloom has transcended the honorable brow. Madam was not slow to perceive it.</p>
                <p><q>What now, Herr William?</q></p>
                <p>Herr William groaned, (a bit of an actor  is the honorable member) <q>'Tis a matter of conscience,</q> said he, <q>Yes, madam, and serious at that. Why, here am I seventeen miles from a barber and just recalling that I promised the good wife to get a haircut!</q></p>
                <p><q>Tut,</q> snapped Madam, <q>you're all alike, ploughman or politician. But you're not so bad about the head. Come to think of it, 'twas only your bristling thatch I had much recollection of after hearing you the first time. Twenty years ago that was, and the wind blowing and you bawling in the teeth of it like an auctioneer. tut I that hair of yours bristling mad-like will please the old timers I'm thinking!</q></p>
                <p>Herr William shook his head. <q> 'Tisn't the hair, woman, that's worrying me 'tis the promise! What with my sitting in the hotel an hour writing to the wife when I might have been hunting a barber and now the doggone celebration plumb upon me...</q></p>
                <p><q>Ah well, well, if that's the how of it,</q> said Madam bouncing up and going to a cupboard. <q>It's myself will make you presentable.</q></p>
                <p>The behind-handedness of men irritates Fru Bjornson not a little. They learn so slowly! In apologizing for the old house, that it wasn't modern and snugger and more suitable to the present need of two old people, she harked back to this grievance. It took so long to bring a man to reason––and having done it 'twasn't likely he'd admit it! Especially was it true of a man who had sort of run down in the hands of two former wives. Madam is a first and a third.</p>
                <p>Why, when she came to take charge of the old house there wasn't a likely spot in it. Rusty pots and pans, cracked dishes, and not a scrap of wholseom paint anywhere! Inside nor out, not even calsomine; nor yet an inch of fly netting! And nothing but wooden beds to sleep on! Fru Bjornson made a sound between a sigh and a snort at the thought of those wooden atrocities. Kerosene baths and plenty of hot water and soap had helped some––but nothing to boast of. This thorn in her puritan flesh had been removed by a just Providence in a singular way. <q>Mischief's mischief,</q> admitted the spry old lady, <q>but sometimes it's a blessing. 'Twas the mischief of Johann's youngest son, by his second wife––the sicklish one before me––that finally rid me of those pesky beds. Made a fire in the mattress, did that young rascal, and then scared to death at what he'd done pulled the blankets over his head! Saints above! What with the smoke belching out of the room like a roaring volcano and that child tangled up in the burning blankets, 'twas enough to give you a turn. But thanks be to God I had sense enough to pitch all that tarnation junk out the window! Just so. It's taking hold of opportunity when she's sort of flitting by that gets you on. The insurance money got me newbeds––iron ones you may well guess––and brand new mattresses. Good land! I ain't felt just right about taking so much for so little, time and time again.</q> Madam paused to reflect. <q>No, 'twasn't wickedness drove Johnny.<foreign xml:lang="is">Nu ja</foreign>, the ways of Providence is past finding out! And barring a little skin and the whole of his hair he wasn't so much the worse for all the fright it give us.</q></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Planning a Marriage</head>
                <p>Trivial things Madam spoke of with impatience but never a word of complaint as to the rest. No bitter word of the early struggle when, as a young widow with three small children she had begun her battle for independence in a country whose very language was strange and foreign. Even then Providence had befriended her, she contended. For wasn't it true that her first husband hadn't been taken from her until Berta was ten and so able to watch the others while their mother went out washing. And hadn't the good God inspired one beautiful rich lady to suggest that she accept old clothes instead of money for her wages! Such nice clothes to make over at night when the work was done, to share with other foreign families whos struggles were similarly keen.</p>
                <p>No harsh word either of the first cruel years with Herr Joahnn when the crops failed, or the cattle sickened, and the <q>mouth disease</q> was spreading north from the States cutting down the sheep like flies; years when success seemed as far removed as the stars and herr Johann hobbled about on crutches because of a gangrenous sore that ate most savagely into the bone––a ruthless wound incurred in the relentless battle with stubborn nature! Herr Johann had gone on doggedly for twenty years, toiling, striving, in field and furrow; and keeping time with hisbrave efforts the griim sore at deeper and deeper. Yet it pleases Herr Johann to remember how expert he became swinging from his crutches to a hay rack, and, blanaced there how expertly he had pitched the fragrant hay!</p>
                <p>Madam disliked speaking of that. Thirty-five splinters of bone she had picked, with her tweezers, from that ghastly wound in the last terrible summer! Then one day Herr Johann had fainted on the plough and, overruled at  last had risked the succor of the new hospital in <placeName> <settlement type="city">Medicine Hat</settlement>, <region type="province">Alberta</region><country>Canada</country></placeName>. Now, glory be to God! and the surgeon's skill, he limped just ever so little!</p>
                <p>Behind Herr Johann's back Madam admitted that she had been something of a success. In teh first place their marriage had been her idea. Back in 1905 she had come to him at the behest of the district missionary. Worn from her struggle in the city of Winnipeg, and with her two little girls just back from the hospital after a siege of sclaret fever, the thought of a summer on an Alberta farm had seemes a rare and opportune blessing.</p>
                <!--Continue transcription-->
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>


