<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/DiSA-DHIL/ATN-Schema/refs/heads/main/dist/ATN.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/DiSA-DHIL/ATN-Schema/refs/heads/main/dist/ATN.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PuritansoftheCanadianWest1">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Puritans of the Canadian West</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcriber</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:SL1">Sydney Lines</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoder</resp>
                    <name ref="pers:SL1">Sydney Lines</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Digital Scholarship in the Arts</distributor>
                <distributor>Digital Humanities Innovation Lab</distributor>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>
                    <!--Information about the source file. If it's
                  a primary source, use a <bibl> or <msDesc>;
                  if born digital, use <p>Born Digital</p>-->
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <schemaRef url="https://github.com/DiSA-DHIL/ATN-Schema/blob/main/sch/ATN.odd"/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="atn:DocType" target="atn:PrimarySource"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <pb n="34"/>
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>Puritans of the Canadian West</head>
            <opener>
                <byline>By <name ref="pers:LGS1">Laura Goodman Salverson</name></byline>
                <byline>Illustrated by <name ref="pers:GOL1">Galbraith O'Leary</name></byline>
            </opener>
            <p>Every kind of people and every kind of faith rub shoulders on the plains, and none loses righteousness thereby. Even communism is here, not in fancy nor theory, but the thing itself. And to the unbiased, dull it seems and incontestably stupid.</p>
            <p>Doubtless the guardian genius of the west chuckles at her own astuteness and acumen, for nowehere could better proof be found of the unfitness of mortals at this particular stage of evolution to participate in such a scheme than can be had in these communities themselves. They are the best possible cure for the fever of communism. Such a settlement may be visited by whosoever has courage to go back, as it were, into the much lamented period of puritanical conscience, stock and pillories and the fear of God.</p>
            <p>Corporeally speaking, the settlement in question lies in a charming valley in Alberta. The good people thereof are <trait type="ethnicity"><label>Ethnicity</label><desc>German Hutterites</desc></trait> or, as they explain, border-people––people from the border of Germany and Russia. German, at any rate, is the language they now speak and in their solemn faces and drab righteousness one may visualize with little difficulty the Puritan fathers, not forgetting the patient, browbeaten Puritan mothers.</p>
            <p>The Hutterites are dedicated to religion. As I was gravely told, man's mission on earth is only to wait the paradise to come. Hence, according to them, ambition is vain and liable to lead one into sin and the painful consequence thereof.But they are an efficient body, none the less, and singular in the records of religious orders, expend no little thought upon diminishing the hardship of manual labor for women as well as men.</p>
            <p>Be t confessed at once that my first impression of the colony not a flattering one. I thought I had accidentally dropped into an experimental stock farm. the buildings had all the appearance of model barns; substantial, ugly, all alike and set row on row. But I was shortly disillusioned, for no sooner had the car come to a halt before on of the lnog rambling buildings, than out of every nook and cranny poured a truly alarming army of young Hutterites.</p>
            <p>After this reception by the rising generation the head of the colony, the minister, made his appearance. Being assured that we would not take any pictures of the people––it being against God to amk any graven image of any living thing––we were courteously invited to see the colony. There was much to admire. The buildings are all goos and sound and fitted up for convenience if not comfort. There is a general dining room for adults, another for children under fourteen, and a kind of kindergarten for babies. Once the baby no longer requires the more tender care if is given over into the charge of the old ladies of the colony who, it is certain, think little enough of the task though they perform the necessary duties in their appointed turn without controversy. The babies have also a rest-room, poorly ventilated but arm and clean, where they have their daily naps.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Interest in Sinful Garments</head>
                <p>The kitchen is fitted up with huge stoves and water is piped right to the cauldrons thereon. Bread is baked in modern ovens such as our bakeries use<note type="editorial" resp="pers:SL1">Who is our? It seems Canada here rather than Icelanders.</note>, and the bread was light and wholesome and appetzing. There is also a general laundry, as modern as can be, and the cellars and root-house are orderly and speak loudly for the thrift and frugality of this people.</p>
                <p>Superficially speaking, there seems much to praise and little to blame. Want is negligible, childhood safe, and old age freed of the terrors of pauperism. Everyone shares alike. As the minister said truthfully, no one ought to be without the necessities of life and no one more than he needs. The difficulty evidently lies in judging what man's true necessity is. The Hutterites have it simplified to food and shelter and garments for the body. Their souls are stayed upon the lord and that suffices them. None the less, it did not prevent the ladies after their first fear of the heathen, from taking a decided interest in my sundry sinful garments.</p>
                <p>Fortunately for me I was invited to the minsister's rooms, his daughter having been delegates to take me round the colony, where I suddenly found myself the centre of curious interest.</p>
                <p>Said one kind dame, whoom I had mistaken for a grandmother only to learn she one year older than myself: <q>What kind of cloth is that?</q></p>
                <p><q>Velvet,</q> said I apologetically.</p>
                <p><q>What's that?</q> asked she, and without more ado plunged forward and picked up as much of my skirt as might be in her enquiring fingers.</p>
                <p><q>Soft,</q> said she, <q>nice and soft. Feel, feel.</q> And all the ladies present had a <q>feel</q> of the uplifted skirt. They were not at all like the Puritan ladies after that, but had a <q>feel</q> of everything visible and what should have been invisible also.</p>
                <p><q>What kind stocking?</q> asked the minister's daughter with a decidedly frivolous gleam in her eye.</p>
                <p><q>Silk,</q> said I in a whisper.</p>
                <p><q>Too thin,</q> said the grandmother my own age, <q>much too thin, and that shirt . . .!</q> Words failed her. <q>Your knees, lady,</q> said she in a motherly voice, <q>will get stiff, very stiff by and by.</q> Then the sleeves of my frock came in for much discussion. Such sleeves were certainly a feeble defense against the cold. Nevertheless they all had a feel of the sleeves and one young girl told me how very nice it seemed on the arm.</p>
                <p>I began to wonder then about the fate of religion in this colony, and also to understand the wooden expression of the women's faces. They certainly are not overworkes, these ladies, housework is portioned out to them impartially. Cooking one weeke, washing th next, baking thereafter, sewing to follow; all with the conscientious regard for what is just and equal. This, the minister said, so that no set of women get too <q>fed up</q> with one kind of work. Oh, yes, the men who must go into the wicked world for necessary supplies and also to market the communities' goods liven the day with an occasional slang word now and again.</p>
                <p>But despite all this it is apparent to the most superficial that the life of the Hutterite women is drear in the extreme. They lef me to see a minister's grandchildren and the mother has a sweet sad face. A mere girl she must have been judging from the age of the matron I had mistaken for a grand-dame. The baby was as clean and well cared for as love could make it, though the tiny thing had already a black cap on its innocent head.</p>
                <p>The minister's daughter, she with the lively gleam in her eye and who, by the way, ate sunflower seed swithout let or hindrance the whole time, the shells just raining down her black habit like chaff on a threshing floor, explained that this baby was sister to another that had died last year . . . and another before that. Then she bent forward mysteriously. <q>Look, lady,</q> said she, <q>you come back summer time. Nice here then, young chickens, young geese, mush green everywhere.</q></p>
                <p><q>Perhaps,</q> said I.</p>
                <p><q>Oh, yes, you come . . . you come and bring machine-box (by which she meant my camera), you come, please lady, and make picture of this baby.</q></p>
                <p>I looked at her and at the poor young mother who evidently dared say nothing and undoubtedly shuddered in her soul for such a sinful request; but she sewed very fast on the little cap in her hands and her breast rose and fell stormily.</p>
                <p><q>But,</q> said I, <q>I could not do that. The minister has trusted me not to do anything against the rules of the colony.</q></p>
                <p>His daughter ate another handful of sunflower seed. <q>That old one,</q> said she, <q>nevermind him. You take baby all the same.</q></p>
                <p>And that, thought I, proved that the serpent was on the job as religiously as ever even in a Hutterite village. Thereafter they hinted that if there was any possible way of getting pieces of cloth––not too bright, you understand––they'd love it dearly to make caps for the babies. Making caps for the babies was the only recreation open to them that I could discover. Sarah, that was the minister's daughter, was about to be married. Right on the spot she invited me to come and what is more, several weeks later proferred the invitation again. She was very indifferent about it, however, though the wedding would be a <q>good time,</q> but children she told me were no good, <q>not like them much only when babies!</q></p>
                <p>I saw the point, quite, when a dozedn or more pushed and pummeled me into the schoolhouse in their eagerness to show me that they were indeed being taught all kinds of knowledge. As they shoved me through the door every last one had to give a flying feel to my coat. It was very funny they thought that i shoul go about in the skins of animals ilke a savage. very funny indeed, and such a queer hat I had, too, it must hurt the head and maybe make for me a sickness. The children through with me, I rejoined my companion who all the while had been in the company of the minister. Health, it happened, was the topic under discussion.</p>
                <p>Sickness, the minister assured us, was rare in the colony. <q>You have much sickness in the city,</q> said he, <q>because of cakes and candy and much tea and riotous living.</q> Then, to show that nature is contradictory everywhere, he insisted that we come to the dining room to have a little something in the way of refreshment. This long barren chamber was scrupuously clean, with nicely varnished tables running down the centre and floors of concrete. Whilst he explained to us teh habit of his people, their community life, and tabulated for us the number of cattle, sheep and horses in their possessions, the ladies hurried to make coffee, fried eggs and cut bread enough to stay the hunger of a threshing gang.</p>
                <p>The minister proved a very kindly sort of person and answered all our questions without evasion or any show of resentment. He told us that if the rules of the community were broken the offender was cast into the world, excommunicated according tot he good old rule. But, he hastened to add, that if the culprit repented they of course took him back and administered no punishment whatever. <q>Sure,</q> said he, <q>it stands in God's word that must forgive.</q></p>
                <p>The men seemed quite happy. They worked outside in groups, mining the coal on their own land, caring for teh cattoe, seeing to the crops. They have also an up-to-date machinist who makes all repairs, and uses every broken bit of machinery to some good end; for instance, making new teeth for old saws out of material that most farmers would discard as useless. The young men seem very ambitious to have a model farm and read every sort of magazine they can get on agriculture and mechanics. the women have no such interests to sustain them. They may not even indulge in the old, old pastime of crochet and fancy work, for with all personal adornment taboo what should they do with such fripperies? And with nothing in the way of a home, save a bedroom or two to which the family retires at night, what is the need of cushions or tidies or such like?</p>
                <p>These rooms were airy and clean, some having excellent floors, painted or varnished They contained for the most part a bed or two, usually a crib also, and a number of chairs. the beds were not not made up according to our conception but had the clothes rolled into a bundle, leaving the springs bare. This, I gathered, was because nearly every bed received during the day the clothes allotted to several at night, and often a crib stood on top the whole or extra chairs were piled there to give more floor space in the room.</p>
                <p>Nowhere did I see any remarkable uncleanliness except as applies to the more fastidious care of the body. They were, however, quite as clean in their perso, these people, as any pilgrim, if histories are any criterion of truth. They have their baths, weekly bathing being the standard rather than the exception. and when it came to facial expression the women, at least, looked very mcuh like certain sainted ladies of the medieval ages––mirthless and sad and set apart from earth. Unfortunately, however, the hidoes garb affected by this people for its women has nothing of the quiet charm of the Pilgrim habit. The darkest shades only are worn; mud brown and blacks, and this of the coarsest and most enduring materials and made in the shapeless manner characteristi of the Russian peasantry in general.</p>
                <p>While the coffee was brewing and the minsiter regaled us with his talk my companion, who has more courage than discretion, was minded of an old vexation. <q>What,</q> said he, <q>is your attitude toward instant baptism? If a baby dies unbaptized does it cause you much worry?</q></p>
                <p>The minister looked mildly surprised. <q>Why, no,</q> said he. <q>Why should it? what can a little child know of right or wrong?</q></p>
                <p>Well, thought I, not a bad beginning that toward a foundation on which to build a broader tolerance. The minister, by the way, carried a mussy infant on his arm for a good while with commendable patience and an unaffected show of affection.</p>
                </div>
           <div>
               <head><q>Never Sick in My Life!</q></head>
            <p>By this time the coffee was boiled and the grandmotherly matron of thirty-odd served us with a liberalness that would be hard to excel. Three or four younger women trailed in to watch the show and when i could positively drink no more, the acting hostess filled my cup again. <q>No, no,</q> said I, <q>it is impossible . . .!</q> but might have spared my agonized apology, for with a broad grin, she sent the cup sailing down table toward the specttaors, four of whom took a hasty sip and doubtless had thereby transgressed to the point of rashness. The minister, wise man, kept right on talking just as if nothing had happened!</p>
               <p>When his daughter had had her sip, up she hopped and literally pouncing on me, said: <q>Come along, come along, so we got house plants to show you.</q> So out I trotted again and for my efforts was shown a row of young geraniums that were doing their brave best to enliven the bleakness of the sister-in-law's room.</p>
               <p>But there was more to see than the geraniums. As handsome an old man as one could wish for glanced up self-consciously from a hasty toilet as we tumbled in. He showed admirable poise, however, and quite as if he were accustomed to such interruptions any say in the week, proceeded to comb his beard. Now, a beard can be either a very agreeable appendage to an aged face or a veritable horror. In this case it was exceedingly agreeable. The kind of fine gray beard we associate with the prophets and patriarchs of old. Though they, poor dears, most likely had no such splendid passion for keeping it smooth as had this old gentleman. His toilet done, he faced me in fatherly fashion.</p>
               <p><q>Where's your man?</q> said he. Not harshly, you understand, but in the tone of voice one uses to wayward children. On hearing that this very necessary protector was indeed not far off, was talking, in fact, to the head man of the village, he rewarded me with a smile. <q>That's good,</q> said he, <q>that's very good. Now I a pure Russian. Pure Russian and seventy––never sick in my life!</q> With which information he betook hiimself out to have a look at <q>the master</q>.</p>
               <p>When we were alone again, the minister's daughter, two other ladies and I, she returned to the subject of the baby. <q>You come sure again and take baby. We like company. Some folks think not; say we live all like cattle, you know different. We like people that like us––you come again, lady, and take baby</q>.</p>
               <p>Outside in the very bare and dismal yard the motor horn reminded me that were some sixty miles between me and home. <q>Thank you,</q> said I, as gracefully and as gratefully as I could. <q>I will come again</q>.</p>
               <p>But, as I climbed into the car and waved good-bye to some thirty friendly human beings who done their level best to make a stranger's unheralded visit pleasant, I was reminded of the sad faced young mother and her delicate little baby. <q>Yes, I will come again,</q> I smiled. But I am not so sure but that some one else will have taken baby.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>

